Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 9 -- Letters to Franklin 1787-1790 Mss.B.F85inventory09
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 9 -- Letters to Franklin
1787-1790
Mss.B.F85inventory09
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
404 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Buffon, comte de
    Scope and Contents note
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter with the detailed account of the régime he observed in order to rid himself of the stone; would follow his example, if he had not discovered that his sufferings were due to another cause. Good wishes for his future health and happiness.
    (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Acknowledging the second volume of the American [Philosophical Society's] Transactions with the honorable and complimentary letter published therein. Sending three copies of his book on Vegetables. Business dealings with Mr. [Samuel] Wharton and Mr. [Francis] Coffyn; reasons for thinking them both, rogues and scoundrels; cannot understand their holding public office; thinks they can both be scared into making restitution. Question of two Loan Certificates which he wishes realized immediately, and the money sent to him; has written several times on this subject to Mr. John Williams, of Boston, with no result. His interest in seeing American newspapers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Has received from Mr. [John Hyacinth de] Magellan £210 on account of the [American] Philosophical Society at Philadelphia [the principal sum of the Society Magellanic Fund]; ready to have Franklin's bills to that amount.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Rumford, Jonathan. Wilmington
    Recalls himself to Franklin's remembrance; his father, the farmer, is dead; encloses a paper which he desires to have published if Franklin thinks it will be of use to the people.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Sharp, Granville. London
    Sending by Colonel Forest a copy of the second edition of his tract on Congregational Courts together with his tracts on Free Militia. Had hoped his writings would have convinced the Americans that the establishment of a free government is not so difficult as the late Convention seems to have apprehended; discusses the question in detail; his attempts to establish a free government by Frank pledge at Sierra Leone on the coast of Africa, frustrated by the wickedness and intemperance of the settlers; does not despair of finally succeeding. Question of forming a staple paper currency. Wisdom of preserving a sufficient proportion of common ground around every town and village.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Randolph, Gov. Edmund. Richmond
    Sending enclosed the memorial of Col. Charles Simms; assured that Franklin will do everything which may, with propriety, tend to his relief.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 11; A.L.S. 4p.; Rumford, Jonathan. Wilmington
    A tirade against sharpers and stock-jobbers and an earnest plea to the rulers of America to fulfill all public contracts and to render justice to her public creditors.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Lavaysse, Puchelberg and Co. L'Orient
    Has two boxes, one of books, the other of trees, received from Mr. [Ferdinand] Grand. The package sent them has been sent to Mr. Grand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    His reasons for having sent Mr. [John] O'Connor to Franklin with a letter of recommendation; if anything to the gentleman's disadvantage has come to Franklin's knowledge, begs to be informed of it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Churchman, George. East Nottingham
    Concerning a plan to found an institution for the education of the poorest children, orphans and minors who will otherwise grow up in utter ignorance; beginnings of such a Charity School already started in Nottingham; question of bringing the matter before the Legislature.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Price, Richard. Newington Green
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter by Mr. [Philip] Nicklin. Death of his wife in September. The second volume of Transactions of the [American] Philosophical Society not yet received. Sent him by [Rt. Rev.] Dr. [William] White a volume of his sermons. Desire of the Baron Maseres to know the nature of the method mentioned by Franklin for paying off the National debt.
    Bibliography
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 283).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 January 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Armstrong, John Jr. Philadelphia
    Desiring to know if Franklin wishes the Board Meeting to take place at his house or at the State House.
    A.E. by Franklin. Electing to have it take place at his own house, because of the uncertainty of the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 1; A.L.S. 5p.; Muller, François Louis de. Nessels
    Submits a plan of government, or a Constitution, composed of several Articles, for the Thirteen States of the American Federation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Hartley, David. London
    He and his brother both out of Parliament, so that his political information is second hand; the promised treaty between France and England; talk of other treaties with European powers; should rejoice to hear of one with America. Question of sending newspapers back and forth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 8; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Jay, John
    Had it not been for the Act which confines the appointment of Consuls to citizens, Sir Edward Newenham's request would doubtless have been granted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Whatley, George. London
    Reflections on the Philadelphia Bank. Thanking him for the medallion. Benefits of free trade. Question of coining in America. His age as compared with Franklin's.
    (In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Hewson, Mary
    Investment of money. American weather as variable as English weather.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Churchman, John. Philadelphia
    Concerning certain discoveries he has made; desires neither the conclusion nor the principles on which it is founded to be made known.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 14; A.L.S. 3p.; La Rouchefoucauld, Duc de
    Acknowledging the Catalogue of the Trees and Schrubs of America. by Mr. [Humphry] Marshall. Grief they have experienced through the loss of his sister. His friendship with the Marquis de la Fayette and their constant talk of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Herschel, William. Slough near Windsor
    Acknowledging his election as a member of the American Philosophical Society. Sends a catalogue of new nebulae and clusters of stars.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 569).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Whitehurst, John. London
    Acknowledging his election as a member of the learned [American] Philosophical Society; begs the Society to accept a copy of his Inquiry; as soon as it is out of press, will send a copy of his next work, viz.: An attempt to obtain invariable measures from the mensuration of time, etc. If copies of the Standard Troy Weight will be acceptable, they are at Franklin's service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Garrigues, Edward. Philadelphia
    Desiring Franklin to appoint a time to settle his account with the estate of Eden Haydock, deceased.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Richardson, Jacob. Newport
    Forwarding Franklin two packets deliverd to him by Capt. James Nixon, From Hamburg. His father-in-law, Capt. Elnathan Hammond, sends his compliments.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Varnum, James Mitchel. New York
    As the Efforts of genius are ever pleasing to great minds, takes the liberty of sending Franklin the enclosed pamphlet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Lamont, Aeneas. Baltimore
    Informed by Mr. [Francis] Childs of Franklin's intention to establish a letter-foundry; desires to know what kinds of type Franklin has on hand and upon what terms he could furnish them; intends establishing a printing office in Winchester, Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Business of the printing-office.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Belcamp
    Introducing Mr. Henry Owen who served aboard Count d'Estaing's fleet, thereby forfeiting all hopes of promotion in his native land; recommends him to Franklin's kind offices and friendly advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Jordan, Thomas. London
    Recalling the pleasurable days they spent together and their frequent games of cribbage. Compares Franklin's position as the head of an Empire with his own as the head of a brewery. Sends him by their friend Watmaugh a cask of beer with his best wishes. News of their old friends, [Samuel] Stanley, [Dr. John] Hawkesworth and [Thomas] Fitzmaurice. [William] Herschel's new discoveries. Hopes to meet him in another world.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Dublin
    Anxious to hear from Franklin concerning his son Robert's request. His eldest son engaged to be married; could have gotten a richer bride for him but neither so handsome nor so well-educated. Voted in favor of the French Treaty of Commerce; finds fault with the duty on French wines. Account of a sanguinary bill on prevent tumultuous risings, lately brought in by their Attorney-General; modifications due to the storm of opposition it raised; Ireland in danger of returning to her former slavery. Surprised at M. Colonne's letter to Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson being printed in the public papers; sends a copy to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Churchman, John. Philadelphia
    Stating his reasons for concluding that the position of the magnetic needle, its dip and variation can be ascertained; means by which one can thus discover longitude at sea.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 March 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Buchanan, George
    sending him a memoir just received from Mr. Quesney who wishes it translated into English in order that his institution may become more generally known; if it meets with Franklin's approbation, begs him to find some one who will translate it and pay himself out of the profits; such kindness will be much appreciated by the President of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences as well as by himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 17; A.N.S. 1p.; Nesbitt, John Maxwell. Philadelphia
    Invitation for dinner from the Society of the Friendly Sons of St. Patrick.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Harmar, Colonel Josiah. Fort Pitt
    Enclosing a return of the Pennsylvania troops in the service of the United States, together with a statement of their present whereabouts. Sends an interpretation of several words of the Delaware and Shawanoe languages; has written to the Missionary of the Moravian Indians for a printed vocabulary of these two languages, which he promises to forward. Acknowledging Franklin's courtesy to him while in Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 22; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Discoveries in chemistry; M. Fourcroy's work;1 hopes to send him another book by this author. L'Assemblé des Notables absorbs the attention of all; balloons would be forgotten were it not for [François] Blanchard; fate of the artists at Javelle. M. [William] Herschel's brilliant discovery of two new satellites; change made in his telescope. Wishes Franklin to attain the age of Nestor.
    General note
    1 Leçons d'Histoire Naturelle et de Chimie.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Roy, Julien David. Paris
    Acknowledging with gratitude Franklin's letter written to him at sea, its subsequent publication in the memoirs of the [American] Philosophical Society and his recent election as a member of that Society. Constantly talking of him with M. Keay, Mme. Cheminot and M. Gudin; Mme. Cheminot's admiration and affection for him. Franklin's letter translated by his brother; sends him the first printed copy; his answer to this, in which he treats of the navigation of rivers, likewise printed. Certain theories about the construction of vessels; promises to send him the models.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 23; A.L.S. 2p.; La Rouchefoucauld, Duc de
    Acknowledging the honor conferred upon him by the American Philosophical Society; offers his services in any capacity which may be of use to the Society. America a great example to the world.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Bowdoin, James. Boston
    Acknowledging Franklin's favors of the sixth and twelfth insts. together with the proceedings of the Council and Assembly of Pennsylvania respecting the rebels against Massachusetts and their proclamation for apprehending several of them. Acknowledging Franklin's congratulations on the success of the measures taken for the suppression of the insurrecion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Malcom, J.P. Philadelphia
    The grandson of Mr. James Peller of Philadelphia; brought up as an engraver; describes a patriotic picture which he desires to engrave and, if permitted, dedicate to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, William Temple. Park
    Concerning the farms he has rented and the arrangements he has made for the farm he intends to occupy. Begs Franklin to send him fifteen pounds which he will repay in a few days when he returns to the city.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 29; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Wilson, -----. Philadelphia
    Desiring the books mentioned to him by Franklin the other day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Gaugnet, -----. Saint Mare
    Served nearly a year under the command of Com. [John] Paul Jones; sends the commission given to him at l'Orient on May 3, 1779, and begs Franklin to present it to Congress with a request to convert it into an officer's brevert; ready at any time to serve in the American navy; owing to his services not being needed at present, has engaged in commerce.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 31; A.L.S. 4p.; Paine, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Announcing his intended departure for Europe in April; desires a letter to the Comte de Vergennes; expects to take his models of bridges with him; will be obliged for a letter to some of the Commissioners in that department. Wishes Franklin's opinion as regards certain points in the construction of his bridge. Letter to Council enclosed offering to show them the two models. [2 p.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 March 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Churchman, John. Philadelphia
    Laying before Franklin, as President of the American Philosophical Society, his conclusions respecting the situation of the magnetic needle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 April 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Churchman, John. Philadelphia
    Quotes several passages from the Old Testament which gave rise to certain speculations on lightning and the Aurora Borealis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 April 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Carroll, John. Georgetown
    Introducing Mr. Digges who is desirous of paying his respects to Franklin during his stay in Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 April 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Childs, Francis
    Regretting his inability to fully comply with his engagement; reasons for his delay; bright hopes for the future. Business of the printing office.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 April 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Bowdoin, James
    Introducing his relative, Mr. Hughes, who desires an opportunity of presenting his respects to so distinguished a character.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 April 6; A.L.S. 1p.; McConnell, Matthew
    Sending a pamphlet for Franklin's perusal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 April 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Short, William. Paris
    In the absence of Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson, forwards certain letters by Mr. [Isaac] Norris of Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 April 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Sevier, John
    Concerning the new State of Franklin; Act of Cession repealed by North Carolina; her attempt to reassume jurisdiction and sovereignty over the State of Franklin; desires to know if their Council of State can count upon Franklin's approbation.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 290; Bigelow, IX, 361).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 April 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Doan, Aaron. Gaol
    Begging Franklin to recommend the enclosed petition favorably; his offense committed at a time when a vindictive spirit unhappily prevailed; his greatest enemies in Bucks County would now be glad to see him at liberty; his good conduct during his long confinement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 April 27; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Roy, Julien David. Paris
    Enclosing a copy of his letter to the Marquis de Castries à propos of his plan to construct a fast ship to ply between London and Paris; took the liberty of placing Franklin's name at the head of his list of subscribers; hopes of a favorable issue. If he were Mme. Cheminot's lover would be jealous of her admiration of Franklin. Sends him the two models of a boat constructed along new lines.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Erkelens, Gosrunus. Chatham, Conn
    Concerning a cobalt mine in his possession which he believes to be the only one discovered in the States; value of this one in trading with China; with proper encouragement, thinks the trade could become an important one; desires Franklin to bring the matter before the Pennsylvania Assembly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel. Norwich Conn
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter of the 14th ult. which, together with the Act of the Pennsylvania Assembly, will be laid before the Legislature of Connecticut; persuaded of their desire to cultivate peace and good harmony.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Short, William. Paris
    Forwarding letters from M. [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy, by the French Consul at New York. The diplomas for the European members of the American Philosophical Society delivered wherever possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Assuring him of her ineffaceable attachment and veneration. Changes in the administration; great hopes arising from the new Minister being a pupil and follower of M. [Anne Robert Jacques] Turgot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Biddle, Charles. Philadelphia
    Nothing can be done for the man in question before the next meeting of the Legislature.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 10; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; L'Enfant, Major Peter Charles. Philadelphia
    Accepting Franklin's invitation to wait upon him the following Saturday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 11; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Thomson, Mr. and Mrs.
    Regretting their inability to wait upon Franklin on Saturday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 14; L.S. 2p.; Bowdoin, James. Boston
    Introducing William Erving, Esq., a brother of Mrs. Bowdoin and a worthy, sensible gentleman. Returns with thanks the manuscript copy of Dr. [John] Jeffries's aerial Voyages.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 14; L.S. Ip.; Byles, Mather. Boston
    Doubts whether Franklin received his former letter; owing to age and palsy, must employ his daughter to repeat his thanks. Congratulates his country on having produced a Franklin.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 303).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. London
    Sending him a treatise on Phlogiston, by Mr. [Richard] Kirwan, together with Mr. [Charles] Dilly's collection of Franklin's late papers. Strongly recommends having the first volume of the [American] Philosophical Transactions reprinted. While at sea, read his observations on Maritime Affairs; will send him shortly his thoughts on that subject.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Coxe, Tench
    Advised by his friends to publish the enclosed essay read before the Society for Political Inquiries.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Flores, Joseph Miguel de
    Deputed by the Royal Academy of History to acknowledge the second volume of the American Philosophical [Society's] Transactions; reflections occasioned by Mr. Otto's dissertation on the discovery of the Western Hemisphere. Sending Various publications of their Society.
    (In Spanish. With translation.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Acknowledging his letter with a copy of the second volume of the American Philosophical [Society's] Transactions; his application of the honor conferred in addressing to him the first dissertation on chimneys. His business with Mr. [Samuel] Wharton; urges certain methods by which Mr. Wharton and Mr. [Francis] Coffyn may be forced to pay the money owing him; relies on Franklin's influence and friendship in this affair. Encloses an open letter to Mr. John Williams which he desires may be attended to at once. Civil war begun in his country. Inquiries after Franklin made by the Emperor [of Austria].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 21; N. in 3d P. 1p.; White, Dr. William
    Accepting the President's invitation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 22; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Brown, Mr
    Acknowledging Franklin's polite invitation; will wait upon him on Thursday at three o'clock.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 22; L.S. 3p.; Ledlie, Hugh. Hartford
    Reminding Franklin of their dining with Gen. Washington, in 1775, and of his having been for thirty years a lodger in the house of his sister, Mrs. [Jane] Mecom; his fruitless attempts to discover her whereabouts and state of health; begs Franklin to favor him with a line on this subject. Desires to know how matters go on at the [Constitutional] Convention. Plan of a new road from Hartford to Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 24; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Pettit, Gen Charles. Philadelphia
    Accepting Franklin's invitation to wait upon him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Campomanès, count de
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter of December 4th and his election to the membership of the American Philosophical Society. Deputed by their Academy of History to send Franklin the first volume of a Spanish and Arabic Dictionary, printed under his direction.
    (In Spanish. Translation. 2p.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 308; Bigelow, IX, 390).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Short, Thomas. Edinburgh
    Offering to repair and improve the telescope made by him for Franklin in 1769; desires no pecuniary acknowledgement for this service; merely wishes to receive an accurate report of the situation and number of his brother's family in America; his intention to make suitable provision for them before he dies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Henry. Baltimore
    Relative to prizes carried into France during the late war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Darwin, Erasmus. Derby
    Writes not only to the philosopher but to the greatest statesman living. Acknowledging Franklin's kindness to his son Robert in France. Description of experiments in electricity performed by a Mr. Bennet, a curate in his neighborhood. Concerning his late translation of the botanical works of Linnaeus.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Gardoqui, Diego